A Register of the Heinrich Bortfeldt Interviews
Hoover Institution Archives
Heinrich Bortfeldt interviews
2001-2006
2002C60
Bortfeldt, Heinrich, interviewer.
6 manuscript boxes (2.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Sound recordings and transcripts of interviews of leaders of the Sozialistische Einheitspartei Deutschlands and of the Partei des Demokratischen Sozialismus, and of other German political and cultural figures, relating to political conditions in East Germany and in reunified Germany.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2002.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
GDR Oral History Project interviews, Hoover Institution Archives
Scope and Content of Collection
The Heinrich Bortfeldt Collection consists of several series of oral history interviews conducted by Bortfeldt, a German historian, between 2001 and 2006. These interviews were a follow-up to an earlier series of interviews conducted in the former East Germany during the period of transition following the fall of the Berlin Wall in 1989 and German reunification in 1990. These earlier interviews, in which Bortfeldt and a number of others participated, can be found in the GDR Oral History Collection in the Hoover Institution Archives. The oral history interviews are available as sound recordings on audio cassette tapes.
For the latter interviews that are represented in this collection, Bortfeldt initially sought to interview leading East German political and governmental figures, such as Egon Krenz, Hans Modrow, Lothar de Maizière and Herbert Häber, as well as West German business and political leaders whose work brought them into contact with East Germany during the 1970s and 1980s, such as Edzard Reuter, Lothar Späth, Kurt Biedenkopf and Björn Engholm. The last major series of interviews in this collection focused on intellectual and artistic figures from the former East Germany, who reflected on their experiences in that country, including the novelist Christoph Hein, the artist Walter Womacka, screenwriter Wolfgang Kohlhaase, theatrical producer Manfred Wekwerth, and actress Gisela May, among others. In addition, a handful of subsequent interviews were conducted with former East German governmental leaders, including the chief of the foreign espionage division of the Ministry of State Security (Stasi), Markus Wolf.
With a few exceptions, transcripts were provided by Bortfeldt for all of the recorded interviews. The first series in this finding aid, the transcripts, is arranged by chronologically-grouped subseries, according to when the interviews were conducted, and then alphabetically within each subseries.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Sozialistische Einheitspartei Deutschlands.; Partei des Demokratischen Sozialismus (Germany); Communism--Germany.; Socialism--Germany.; Germany (East)--Politics and government.; Germany--Politics and government--1990-; Phonorecords.
Collection Contents
- Transcripts, 2001-2006 (Box 1-3)
  - Transcripts Group 1, 2001-2002 (Folder 1)
    - Photographs, undated (Folder 1:1)
    - Lothar Bisky, 2001 December 12 (Folder 1:2)
    - Peter-Michael Diestel, 2001 December 17 (Folder 1:3)
    - Werner Eberlein, 2001 October 23 (Folder 1:4)
    - Rainer Eppelmann, 2002 March 22 (Folder 1:5)
    - Herbert Häber, 2001 October 30 (Folder 1:6)
    - Egon Krenz, 2001 November 15 (Folder 1:7)
    - Horst Grunert, 2002 March 4 (Folder 1:8)
    - Lothar de Maizière, 2001 December 17 (Folder 1:9)
    - Joachim Misselwitz, 2002 January 28 (Folder 1:10)
    - Hans Modrow, 2001 November 22 (Folder 1:11)
    - Hans Modrow, 2001 November 22 (Folder 1:12)
    - Gustav Adolf Schur, 2002 February 12 (Folder 1:13)
    - Gabriele Zimmer, 2002 January 15 (Folder 1:14)
    - Gabriele Zimmer, 2002 January 15 (Folder 1:15)
  - Transcripts Group 2, 2002-2003 (Folder 1)
    - Jürgen Aretz, 2003 January 23 (Folder 1:16)
    - Kurt Biedenkopf, 2003 January 15 (Folder 1:17)
    - Hans-Otto Bräutigam, 2002 November 5 (Folder 1:18)
    - Erhard Eppler, 2002 June 12 (Folder 1:19)
    - Herbert Häber, 2003 February 24 (Folder 1:20)
    - Edzard Reuter, 2003 May 15 (Folder 1:21)
    - Lothar Späth, 2003 April 16 (Folder 1:22)
    - Karsten Voigt, 2003 February 17 (Folder 1:23)
  - Transcripts Group 3, 2003-2005 (Folder 2)
    - Christine Bergmann, 2003 October 23 (Folder 2:1)
    - Björn Engholm, 2003 November 22 (Folder 2:2)
    - Erich Hahn, 2003 November 6 (Folder 2:3)
    - Reinhard Höppner, 2004 April 14 (Folder 2:4)
    - Franz Jahsnowsky, 2003 January 20 (Folder 2:5)
    - Gisela May, 2004 January 16 (Folder 2:6)
    - Rolf Schwanitz, 2003 October 29 (Folder 2:7)
    - Hans Jochen Vogel, 2003 October 24 (Folder 2:8)
    - Axel Weisener, 2003 March 24 (Folder 2:9)
  - Transcripts Group 4, 2003-2006 (Folder 2-3)
    - Theo Adam, 2004 September 10 (Folder 2:10)
    - Bruno Flierl, 2006 October 30 (Folder 2:11)
    - Victor Grossman, 2004 September 2 (Folder 2:12)
    - Birgid Gysi, 2006 March 2 (Folder 2:13)
    - Heidrun Hegewald, 2005 January 10 (Folder 2:14)
    - Christoph Hein, 2006 June 14 (Folder 2:15)
    - Bernhard Heisig and Gudrun Brüne, 2005 November 18 (Folder 2:16)
    - Klaus Höpke, 2004 September 16 (Folder 2:17)
    - Winfried Junge, 2006 April 26 (Folder 2:18)
    - Jo Jastram, 2005 November 11 (Folder 2:19)
    - Hermann Kant, 2004 September 24 (Folder 2:20)
    - Walter Kaufmann, 2005 February 2 (Folder 2:21)
    - Wolfgang Kohlhaase, 2005 March 23 (Folder 2:22)
    - Erich Loest, 2006 March 29 (Folder 3:1)
    - Erik Neutsch, 2004 November 10 (Folder 3:2)
    - Gisela Oechelhäuser, 2005 October 26 (Folder 3:3)
    - Klaus Renft, 2005 March 22 (Folder 3:4)
    - Helmut Sakowski, 2004 November 24 (Folder 3:5)
    - Landolf Scherzer, 2005 December 10 (Folder 3:6)
    - Frank Schöbel, 2005 November 16 (Folder 3:7)
    - Peter Schreir, 2005 April 22 (Folder 3:8)
    - Willi Sitte, 2004 November 9 (Folder 3:9)
    - Peter Sodann, 2006 February 28 (Folder 3:10)
    - Peter Strang, 2005 May 27 (Folder 3:11)
    - Barbara Thalheim, 2005 October 5 (Folder 3:12)
    - Jutta Wachowiak, 2005 May 11 (Folder 3:13)
    - Manfred Wekwerth, 2004 August 30 (Folder 3:14)
    - Walter Womacka, 2004 November 16 (Folder 3:15)
  - Transcripts Group 5, 2004-2006 (Folder 3)
    - Gerhard Beil, 2006 March 29 (Folder 3:16)
    - Herbert Häber, 2004 November 17 (Folder 3:17)
    - Heinz Kessler, 2005 January 5 (Folder 3:18)
    - Jörg Schönbohm, 2006 March 30 (Folder 3:19)
    - Manfred Stolpe, 2006 October 20 (Folder 3:20)
    - Bernd Stange, 2005 June 7 (Folder 3:21)
    - Markus Wolf, 2004 December 14 (Folder 3:22)
    - Markus Wolf, 2005 March 1 (Folder 3:23)
    - Friedrich Wolff, 2005 July 18 (Folder 3:24)
- Cassette Tapes, 2001-2006 (Box 4-6)
  - Theo Adam, 2004 September 10 (Folder 4)
  - Jürgen Aretz, 2003 January 23 (Folder 4)
  - Egon Bahr, 2002 June 3 (Folder 4)
    2 cassettes
  - Gerhard Beil, 2006 March 29 (Folder 4)
  - Christine Bergmann, 2003 October 23 (Folder 4)
  - Kurt Biedenkopf, 2003 January 15 (Folder 4)
  - Lothar Bisky, 2001 December 12 (Folder 4)
  - Hans-Otto Bräutigam, 2002 November 5 (Folder 4)
  - Gudrun Brüne and Bernhard Heisig, 2005 November 18 (Folder 4)
  - Peter-Michael Diestel, 2001 December 17 (Folder 4)
  - Werner Eberlein, 2001 October 23 (Folder 4)
  - Björn Engholm, 2003 November 22 (Folder 4)
  - Rainer Eppelmann, 2002 March 22 (Folder 4)
  - Erhard Eppler, 2003 June 12 (Folder 4)
  - Bruno Flierl, 2006 October 30 (Folder 4)
  - Günther Gaus, 2002 June 5 (Folder 4)
  - Victor Grossman, 2004 September 2 (Folder 4)
  - Horst Grunert, 2002 March 4 (Folder 4)
  - Birgid Gysi, 2006 March 2 (Folder 4)
  - Herbert Häber, 2001 October 30 (Folder 4)
  - Herbert Häber, 2003 February 24 (Folder 4)
  - Herbert Häber, 2004 November 17 (Folder 4)
  - Erich Hahn, 2003 November 6 (Folder 4)
  - Christoph Hein, 2006 June 14 (Folder 4)
  - Klaus Höpke, 2004 September 16 (Folder 4)
  - Reinhard Höppner, 2004 April 14 (Folder 4)
  - Franz Jahsnowsky, 2003 January 20 (Folder 4)
  - Jo Jastram, 2005 November 11 (Folder 4)
    Cassette 1 of 2
  - Jo Jastram, 2005 November 11 (Folder 5)
    Cassette 2 of 2
  - Winfried Junge, 2006 April 26 (Folder 5)
  - Hermann Kant, 2004 September 24 (Folder 5)
  - Walter Kaufmann, 2005 February 2 (Folder 5)
  - Heinz Kepler, 2005 January 5 (Folder 5)
  - Walther Kieb, 2002 September 3 (Folder 5)
  - Wolfgang Kohlhaase, 2005 March 23 (Folder 5)
  - Egon Krenz, 2001 November 15 (Folder 5)
  - Erich Loest, 2006 March 29 (Folder 5)
  - Lothar de Maizière, 2001 December 17 (Folder 5)
  - Gisela May, 2004 January 16 (Folder 5)
  - Joachim Misselwitz, 2002 January 28 (Folder 5)
  - Hans Modrow, 2001 November 22 (Folder 5)
  - Edgar Most, 2003 January 8 (Folder 5)
  - Erik Neutsch, 2004 November 10 (Folder 5)
  - Gisela Oechelhäuser, 2005 October 26 (Folder 5)
  - R. Riebig, 2002 October 7 (Folder 5)
  - Klaus Renft, 2005 March 22 (Folder 5)
  - Edzard Reuter, 2003 May 15 (Folder 5)
  - Helmut Sakowski, 2004 November 24 (Folder 5)
  - Landolf Scherzer, 2005 December 10 (Folder 5)
  - Frank Schöbel, 2005 November 16 (Folder 5)
  - Jörg Schönbohm, 2006 March 30 (Folder 5)
  - Peter Schreier, 2005 April 22 (Folder 5)
  - Gustav Adolf Schur, 2002 February 12 (Folder 5)
  - Rolf Schwanitz, 2003 October 29 (Folder 5)
  - Willi Sitte, 2004 November 9 (Folder 5)
  - Peter Sodann, 2006 February 28 (Folder 6)
  - Lothar Späth, 2003 April 16 (Folder 6)
  - Bernd Stange, 2005 June 7 (Folder 6)
  - Manfred Stolpe, 2006 October 20 (Folder 6)
  - Barbara Thalheim, 2005 October 5 (Folder 6)
  - Bernhard Vogel, 2003 February 14 (Folder 6)
  - Hans Jochen Vogel, 2003 October 24 (Folder 6)
  - Karsten Voigt, 2003 February 17 (Folder 6)
  - Richard von Weizsäcker, 2002 June 18 (Folder 6)
  - Manfred Wekwerth, 2004 August 30 (Folder 6)
  - Axel Weisener, 2003 March 24 (Folder 6)
  - Markus Wolf, 2004 December 14 (Folder 6)
    Use copy reference number: 2002c60_a_0000557
  - Markus Wolf, 2005 March 1 (Folder 6)
    Use copy reference number: 2002c60_a_0000556
  - Friedrich Wolff, 2005 July 18 (Folder 6)
  - Walter Womacka, 2004 November 16 (Folder 6)
  - Gabriele Zimmer, 2002 January 15 (Folder 6)